A Guide to the Patrick Acheson Collection 1920 - 1952
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Patrick Acheson Collection 1920 - 1952
Thomas Balch Library
SC 0152
Less than .33 cubic ft..
This collection was found in a house on Cornwall Street, Leesburg, after the Patrick Acheson family had relocated. It consists primarily of photographs, handwritten notes, a 1920 U.S. passport, plus a program for the Foreign Correspondents Dinner (1941).
Patrick Bernard Victor Montagu Acheson (1915-2005)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Catherine Darne, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2019.0019
Historical Information
The Hon. Patrick Bernard Victor Montagu Acheson (1915-2005) lived at 207 Cornwall Street, Leesburg and in Waterford, Loudoun County. Patrick was born in England, the second son of the 5th Earl of Gosford (1877-1954). The 5th Earl had married an American, Caroline Mildred Carter (1889-1965) in 1910. Her father, John Ridgely Carter (1862-1944), was the U.S. Ambassador to Romania at the time of the wedding. This marriage between the English aristocracy and a high society American family reflects the intertwining of the two social groups in this period. John Singer Sargent painted portraits of both Caroline Carter and John R. Carter.
The photographs and correspondence in this collection represent the American side of Patrick Acheson's family. The early photographs are from the late Edwardian period at the time of his parents' marriage.
Scope and Content
This collection was found in a house on Cornwall Street, Leesburg, after the Patrick Acheson family had relocated. It consists primarily of photographs, handwritten notes, a 1920 U.S. passport, plus a program for the Foreign Correspondents Dinner (1941). Mr. Patrick Acheson, resident of Leesburg, was the second son of the 5th Earl of Gosford. The photographs are of his mother, an American, his maternal grandparents, a resort hotel in Switzerland (Palazzo Salis), and one photograph of Patrick Acheson and one of his brother, Archibald Acheson, in a Royal Air Force uniform. The majority of the notes are between Louise (surname unknown) and Milly, Countess of Gosford.
The guest list of the Third Foreign Correspondents Dinner-Forum is dated 19 November 1941 and is entitled "What are the Chances for a Nazi Defeat".
Arrangement
Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Patrick Acheson Collection (SC 0152), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Other Finding Aid
Past Perfect catalogue records
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
None
Contents List
    - Correspondence from "Louise", 1941-1952
    - Correspondence, 1947
    - Passport, Alice Morgan Carter, 1920
    - Foreign Correspondents Dinner Guest List, November 19, 1941
    - Photograph [Patrick Acheson]
    - Photograph [Archibald Acheson]
    - Photograph [Group including Countess of Gosford]
    - Photograph [Alice Morgan Carter]
    - Photograph, [John R. Carter]
    - Photograph, [John R. Carter]
    - Photograph, [John R. Carter]
    - Photograph, Soglio, Switzerland
    - Photograph, Palazzo Salis, 1948
    - Photograph, Palazzo Salis